Guide to the Twenty-Six Literary Club records, circa 1910-1994 MS 066
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Twenty-Six Literary Club records
circa 1910-1994
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Twenty-Six Literary Club (Houston, Tex.)
MS 066
3 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
The records of the Twenty-Six Literary Club document the activities of this women's social and philanthropic club established in 1909 by a group of Houston women residing in the Woodland Heights neighborhood. Some members' daughters became students at the Rice Institute (later University) after it opened in 1912 and continued the Club, expanding its membership over the years and engaging in various community projects, including providing scholarships for young women entering Rice.
Biographical Sketch
A group of Houston women residing in the Woodland Heights neighborhood founded a club in 1909, initially calling it "The 26 Club," so named (according to tradition) because their modest homes could accommodate up to 26 guests. To their chagrin, they later discovered that this was also the name of a saloon on Houston Avenue, and promptly changed their name to "The 26 Literary Club" (which for archival purposes has been re-phrased as "The Twenty-Six Literary Club"). The daughters of a number of the original members became students at Rice Institute (later University) after it opened in 1912 and continued the Club, which over time was expanded and, along with its social activities, assumed various philanthropic projects, including providing scholarships for young women entering Rice.
Scope and Contents
Meeting minutes, membership directories, photographs, newsclippings, biographical notes and more document the members and activities of the Twenty-Six Literary Club from 1910-1994.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
The Twenty-Six Literary Club Records were donated January 6, 2004 and August 12, 2005 by Joyce Nagle (Rice, Class of 1944).
Index Terms
Subjects
Book clubs (Discussion groups); Women -- Societies and clubs; Women
Document Types
photographs; corrrespondence; clippings (information artifacts)
Subjects (Persons)
Thigpen, Hazel; Switzer, Beaulah; Taylor, Alberta; Walters, Evelyn; Weisinger, Frances; Vanderslice, Eleanor; Winning, Lucile; Williams, Amy; Winning, Given; Armstrong, Dora; Autry, Hennie; Bond, Mary; Brandenberger, Eleanor; Nagle, Joyce; Cole, Frances; Crabbe, Julia; Cunningham, Edna Mae; Engstron, Verena; Dennard, Kathryn; Kennedy, Bernice; Hamilton, Allene; Lawrence, Lee; Kuhn, Alma; Manning, Maxine; LeGrand, Mary Margaret; McReynolds, Jennie; Pickle, Lee; Richardson, Roxie; Shelby, Ruth; Seamenn, Gwen
Subjects (Corporations)
Twenty-Six Literary Club (Houston, Tex.); Rice University
- Series I: Minutes, 1955-1985, 11220
  - Minutes, 1910-1911, 118969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1913-1916, 1918-1919, 118970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1916-1917, 118971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1922-1929, 118972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1929-1933, 118973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1933-1938, 118975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1947-1949, 118976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1951-1953, 118977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1955-1985 (Folder 1 of 2), 11221 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1955-1985 (Folder 2 of 2), 118974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series II: Directories, 1923-1998, 11211
  - 1911-1929, 11219 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1930-1939, 11218 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1940-1949, 11217 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1950-1959, 11216 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1960-1969, 11215 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1970-1979, 11214 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1980-1989, 11213 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1990-1998, 11212 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series III: General club records, 11199
  - Clippings, 11210 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 11209 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Federations of Women's Clubs, 11208 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Texas Clubwoman, Directory Issue, Sept. 1958, 118978 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Guest Book, April 3, 1957-September 3, 1964, 11207 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Histories and Constitution, 11206 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Notepaper, 11205 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Notes – brief biographies of club members, 11204 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Program lists, annual themes, hostesses, 11203 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Songs, poems, and prayers, 11202 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Special Events (teas and anniversaries), 11201 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Yearbook, 1910-1911 (photocopy), 11200 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1910s-1994, 11188
  - Subseries A: Photographs, 1910s-1980s, 11193 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - ca. 1910: on Rice campus of Mr. Lee Miller, Ruth Shelby, Julia Crabbe, Mr. Given Winning, 11198
    - 1940s: Ms. Black, Ms. Norman, Ms. Duke, Ms. Lavereuax, Ms. Lucile Winning (Mrs. G.W. Winning), Alma Kuhn (Mrs. E.R. Kuhn), Agnes Andrews (Mrs. Wayne Andrews), Ruth Harper (Mrs. Max Harper), Mrs. Frank Cox, Mrs. E.B. Burkhin, Hennie Autry (Mrs. H.S. Autry), Beulah Switzer (Mrs. P.E. Switzer), Ruby Jones (Mrs. J. Jones), Amy Williams (Mrs. O.B. Williams), 11197
    - 1960s: Zelma Schwarts, Berta Black, Bess Gardner, Mrs. Andrews, Mrs. Willbanks, Mrs. McReynolds, Mrs. Richardson, Mrs. Johnson, Mrs. Hammerly, Mrs. Winning, Mrs. Jones, Mrs. Kennedy, 11196
    - 1970s: Frances Cole, Lee Pickle, Bobbie Ozzell, Hazel Thigpen, Mary Bond, Edna Mae Cunningham, Lorena Kobs, Frances Weisinger, Eleanor Vanderslice, Louise Crowell, Alene Edge, Helen Morrison, Joyce Nagle, Alberta Taylor, Frances Moers, Maurine Hardison, Dena Standish, Alma Kuhn, 11195
    - 1980s: Roxie Richardson, Grace Moseley, Mary Margaret LeGrand, Evelyn Wathen, Lee Pickle, Gwen Seammen, Maurine Hardison, Frances Moers, Helen Morrison, Frances Cole, Bernice Kennedy, Dora Armstrong, 11194
  - Subseries B: Portrait album (c. 1920s-?), 11191 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Mrs. J. Lee Norman, Mrs. W.M. Harrell, Mrs. E.L. Crumpacker, Mrs. R. M. Blieke (portrait missing), Mrs. James D. Jones, Mrs. Wayne Andrews, Mrs. H.A. Gardner, Mrs. Robert E. Morse, Mrs. Ralph Walton, Mrs. D.L. Landrum (portrait missing), Mrs. J.L. Klinger Mrs. Ed Walker, Mrs. G. O. Wilson, Mrs. Frank Cox, Mrs. P. Geo. Maercky, Mrs. J.F. Ransome, Mrs. W.J. Morrow, Mrs. R.A. LeRoux, Mrs. T.M. Spence, Mrs. N. H. Dickinson, Mrs. C. K. Wilbanks, Mrs. F.J. Richardson (portrait missing),Mrs. F.M. Stones, Mrs. Winefred Lamoreaux, Mrs. H.S. Autry, Mrs. W. E. Vater, Mrs. Ira J. Allen, Mrs. J. Vandaveer, Mrs. R.H. Swartz, Mrs. J.W. Bond, Mrs. J. I. McGregor, Mrs. L.R. Gripon, Mrs. S.J. Eubank, Mrs. Henry John, Mrs. P.E. Switzer, Mrs. W.R. Shriner, Mrs. Anna M. English (portrait missing), Mrs. F.M. Black, Mrs. G. W. Winning (portrait missing), Mrs. T.F. Gilley, Mrs. W.S. Brandenburger (portrait missing), Mrs. M. Beringe,r Mrs. W.E. Garner, Mrs. J.L. McReynolds, Mrs. A.B. Haynes, Mrs. A.E. Goffe, Mrs. R.E. Avery, Mrs. Carl H. Duke, Mrs. F.M. Allerton, Mrs. Fred Jones, 11192
  - Memorial scrapbook, 1959-1997, 11190 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Containing resolutions of respect composed by club members for members who have passed away.
  - General scrapbook, 1988-1994, 11189 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Featuring: Joyce Nagle, Lee Lawrence, Edna May Cunningham, Mary Margaret LeGrand, Bernice Kennedy, D. Armstrong, Maxine Manning, Evelyn Walters, Lee Pickle, Ruby Clifton, Gwen Seammen, Grace Moseley, Frances Cole, Roxie Richardson, P. Ryan, G. Wilson, M. Hardison, Kathryn Dennard, Alberta Taylor, Y. Nash, C. Nash, A. Suchichi, Verena Engstrom, Allene Hamilton, Glenna Wilson, Mrs. Hrivnatz, Lynn Griggsly